

# Pelayo González Arbués

Date of birth: 1983/11/25

Address: Calle Bravo Murillo, 95. Madrid 28003 | | T: 645463120 | | E-mail: gonzalezpelayo@gmail.com

#### **Motivation**

During my 8 years of professional experience I have mainly worked in data science, specially in the application of statistical learning and econometrics models. More precisely, I am able to perform efficient data manipulation and summarize large amounts of data with the aid of visualization techniques. In addition, I also have the technical skills to estimate causal linkages between variables and to provide decision makers with accurate data forecasts. My long-term career objective is to become a lead data scientist with a specialization on Machine Learning algorithms able to generate added value to companies through rigorous data analysis.

### **Experience**

#### Data analyst – e-Knowledge in Intermodal Transport IT

[Jul. 2014 - Sep. 2015]

Data analyst in International research project <u>eKnow-IT</u> funded by the European Commission. In this position I was responsible to assess transport sector activities and best practices in logistics. Besides reporting about these activities, I was also in charge of coordinating case studies writing and elaborating the dissemination plan and the scientific framework.

- o My role:
  - Database creation (Compiling data from different sources)
  - Data munging
  - Data analysis (Exploratory analysis, linear regression)
  - Reporting to other team members
  - Case study writing
- o Software: R

#### **Economic Consultant. University of Oviedo**

[Sep. 2013- Dec. 2013]

While I was preparing the defense of my doctoral thesis I worked as a consultant in a project for the Spanish Public Service of Employment where accessibility to Employment Offices was evaluated. My role in this project:

- o My role:
  - Data munging (Creation of geo-coded accessibility variables)
  - Drafting reports
- o Software: R

# Economic Consultant – Researcher. University of Oviedo

[Oct. 2008 – Sep. 2013]

In this period I worked on my doctoral thesis where I conducted three empirical research exercises applying statistical and econometric techniques. In the first essay a spatial econometrics model is applied to the study of the economic contribution of transport infrastructure to regional productivity. The second essay is devoted to analyze road freight transportation demand applying a gravity equation in a panel data framework. The last essay aims to study the determinants of modal choice



in long distance trips in Spain through the estimation of a multilevel multinomial model.

In addition, I have actively participated in different consultancy projects:

- Efficiency analysis of Postal Service distribution offices. Project funded by the Postal Sector National Commission. Econometric models were estimated in order to evaluate the efficiency scores of different offices and to estimate a value of the facilities.
  - o My role:
    - Data munging
    - Data analysis: Estimation of Stochastic Frontier Models, efficiency scores computation
    - Drafting reports
  - Software used: Stata and Limdep
- Demand analysis and forecasting of traffic volumes in the seaport of Gijón. Project funded by the Port Authority of Gijón. Statistical and econometrics models were applied to interaction data to obtain flows predictions.
  - o My role:
    - Estimation of linear regression models
    - Drafting reports
  - o Software used: R
- Microdata analysis of road freight movements in Spain. <u>GLOBALOG</u> Project funded by the Spanish Ministry of Public Works.
  - o My role:
    - Database creation
    - Data munging
    - Estimation of panel data models
    - Forecasting future flows among Spanish regions
    - Final reports writing
  - Software: Stata and R

I have also assisted in the teaching of Microeconomics and Microeconomics applied to Tourist Sector courses in the University of Oviedo.

#### **Economic Consultant - FOED**

[Jun. 2008 - Oct. 2008]

Sports Economics Observatory (FOED) is a *think-tank* oriented to the analysis of economic activities related to sports. In summer 2008, I worked in a Project funded by the Town Hall of Gijón that aimed to measure the economic impact of Speed Skating World Championship celebrated in that city.

- o My role:
- Data collection, database creation
- Input/Output models calibration
- o Software: Excel



## Research assistant. University of Oviedo

[Sep. 2007 - Jun. 2008]

In this period I had my first contacts to the creation and management of databases for different consultancy and research projects carried out by the Department of Economics.

**Education** 

Ph.D. in Economics

[Sep. 2010 - Dec. 2013]

Thesis topic: "Essays on Transport Economics". Advisors: Jose F. Baños and Matías Mayor

**M.S., Economics** [Sep. 2007 – Sep. 2008]

Universidad del País Vasco, Universidad de Oviedo and Universidad de Cantabria

**B.S.**, **Economics** [Sep. 2001 - Sep. 2007]

Universidad de León

Other Education

Spatial Econometrics with MATLAB

Oct. 2012

Taught by James Lesage in Universidad Autónoma Madrid

International Autumn School in Spatial Econometrics.

Oct. 2011

Coordinated by José María Montero and Jean Paelinck, Universidad de Castilla La Mancha

Summer School: Spatial Econometrics Advanced Institute.

[Apr. 2011 - May. 2011]

Coordinated by Giusseppe Arbia. University of Roma La Sapienza

Econometric Estimation of Frontier Functions and Economic Efficiency

May. 2008

Taught by Professor William Greene in Instituto de Estudios Fiscales

**Online Education** 

SQL, Stanford Online

[Apr. 2015 – Jun. 2015]

Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python, The Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MITx)

[Jun. 2015 – Aug. 2015]

**Publications** 

Pelayo Arbués; José Baños Pino; Matías Mayor Fernández; Patricia Suárez Cano (2015) <u>Determinants of ground transport modal choice in long-distance trips in Spain</u>, Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice

Pelayo Arbués, José F Baños; Matías Mayor (2015) <u>The Spatial Productivity of Transportation</u> <u>Infrastructure</u>, Transportation Research Part A: Policy and Practice, 75, 166-177

Pelayo Arbués, José Baños Pino (2015) <u>A Dynamic Approach to Road Freight Flows Modeling in Spain</u>, Transportation

Pelayo Arbués; José Baños Pino; Matías Mayor Fernández; Patricia Suárez Cano (2014) Econometric Modelling of Long-Distance Travel. Revista de Economía Mundial. 38, pp. 101 – 126.

Pelayo Arbués; Matías Mayor Fernández; José Francisco Baños Pino (2014) Productivity and accessibility of road transportation infrastructure in Spain in Accessibility and Spatial Interaction. Pp. 177 – 194. Edward Elgar Publishing

Rosa Aza, José F. Baños, Pelayo González, Manuel Llorca (2011) La demanda de transporte de mercancías por carretera en España: Un modelo de datos de panel in *Estudios de Construccion y Transportes*, 115(12):31–48



Grants, Awards and others Spanish Regional Science Association Young Researcher Award

Nov 2013 2010 - 2013

Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship Severo Ochoa funded by Principado de Asturias

Visiting researcher in Vrije Universiteit (Amsterdam, NL) [Apr. 2012 - Jun. 2012]

Visiting researcher in Vrije Universiteit (Amsterdam, NL) [Apr. 2013 - May. 2013]

Participant as a paper presenter in 10 Conferences [2008 - Present]

**Skills** Analytical thinking

Advanced knowledge on statistics and econometrics: Panel data, statistical learning, discrete choice modeling, spatial econometrics.

Coding: STATA and R (Expert). MATLAB, PYTHON and SQL (Basic).

Reporting tools: Microsoft Office, LaTeX and MarkDown.

Excellent written and verbal communication skills. Professional speaking abilities and experience.

Enjoy working as a team member as well as independently

**Interests** Running

Coding: pelayoarbues.github.io

Photography: <u>pelayoarbues.tumblr.com</u>